foreign
[Music]
and today we're going to be learning
about how to balance chemical reactions
so when it comes to chemical reactions
in your chemistry class this is when
things really can get a little
overwhelming but I hope that this video
will help a little bit for you to be
able to learn the basic process so what
is it what is a chemical reaction so the
whole idea behind it is that it's a
process when you have different have
substances that are reacting with each
other so when this happens bonds are
going to be breaking and new bonds are
going to be forming so we're going to
create brand new substances so we're
going to see changes occurring whether
it's in the form of colors gases or
maybe energy and heat being released
there are going to be a lot of things
that we will observe and we can measure
in the lab so one way that we illustrate
this is that scientists like to use
chemical equations to repre represent
these changes to see when chemicals are
reacting so the basic way that this is
actually going to be shown is that on
the left hand side of an equation we'll
write all of our reactants
and what that's going to be showing is
we're going to instead of writing like
an equal sign we're going to write an
arrow saying that this is going to be
yielding or creating different products
so we go from reactants to products so
what's participating and what's being
created now when we are looking at these
different reactions the whole idea
behind it is that we have to conserve
Mass meaning that whatever you are
putting into the reaction it must come
out in the form of matter this is one of
the laws of science
so the in a sense the mass of the
products must equal the mass of the
reactants now are we going to be like
whipping out a balance and trying to see
are we creating the same amount every
time well no we're not going to be doing
that but what we can relate Mass to is
molar mass meaning grams over moles
so in a sense
this tells us that the chemical
equations must be balanced and that the
number of moles of each element on the
left side must equal the number of moles
of the elements on the right side so we
must have the same number of each atom
on both sides so that's the idea
so what's our agenda for today so we're
going to be writing out a bunch of
different chemical equations so we're
going to first write out the unbalanced
equation
we're going to count the number of moles
a k the number of atoms of each element
on both sides and then we're going to be
multiplying these elements by
coefficients or whole numbers so whole
number integers to try to balance them
on both sides so let's try to do that
let's go through a couple of different
examples of how to really showcase this
so if I do let's say the first one here
and I have H2
reacting with O2
to create water
how would I balance this equation so the
first thing you're going to do is you're
going to draw a you're going to have an
imaginary divide right down the middle
right so it has to be the same number of
reactants and same number of products so
what we're going to do is we're going to
write out each species that we have so
we have hydrogen which is one Element
then we have oxygen on both sides and
now what we're going to do is we're
going to count them so we can see from
the subscript on hydrogen we have two
hydrogens on the left
we have two Hydro or two oxygens on the
on the left as well
now when we go to the right hand side
we'll see that okay well we have two
hydrogens and one oxygen and I like to
write these numbers under the species
that we're counting it from so that way
we can keep a little bit better track of
our math
all right so the goal was is to make it
the same number of moles equal on both
sides so what this is kind of showing
for ourselves to draw it is that I have
currently a hydrogen and it's reacting
with and oxygen so we'll draw them as
little orbs
and what that is creating is
an ox essentially creating a water
molecule okay so that is what is
happening here so we have
one orb reacting with another to create
a new thing so reactants go to products
so let's try to balance it so the first
thing you're going to think is oh I got
to multiply
the right side by two so this is a
coefficient so the way that we will show
a coefficient is we put a number out
front so what this is telling you is
that when you multiply that by two it's
the same way as you saying that oh I
have two water molecules
that are now on the right side of the
equation so we have a total of two of
them so is that a balanced equation well
we didn't only multiply the oxygens we
also multiplied the hydrogens by putting
that coefficient there
so now we have a total of four hydrogens
on the right four oxygen or sorry not
four oxygens two oxygens
so now we need to balance our hydrogens
in the way that we can do that is by
adding
A2 in front of that hydrogen so adding
that multiple
and what that's going to do is
essentially tell us that oh
we have two hydrogen molecules reacting
with every one oxygen molecule so in a
sense this is like saying we have two
moles
of H2
one mole
of o2 creates two moles
of H2O and that's the idea behind
chemical equations this is all balance
in terms of elements let's try another
one together
so if I do another
let's say we have a zinc is reacting
with HCL
and what that's going to be creating is
zinc
chloride
and a hydrogen gas
now one other thing that we can do with
chemical equations to tell just
something else your teachers are going
to make you do is you have to label what
phase everything is so if it's a solid
we put an S
if it's aqueous or meaning it's a liquid
in of solution of water that's AQ
or if it's like a liquid we'll use an L
for a liquid but none of these are just
pure pure liquids
or if it's a gas we use a g so I would
get in that habit just because it will
help you be able to figure out what
you're going to see
okay so what is this really showing so
we have a zinc atom
and that's going to be reacting with we
have hydrogen and chlorine
so that's going to be reacting with an H
with a CL so we should do CLS green
so these are going to be reacting with
each other
and it's going to be creating
a zinc chloride so we're going to have a
ion here that's being made
okay and then we're creating H2 so are
we balance on both sides well let's
count so we have one zinc one hydrogen
put that on the right spot for ourselves
one chlorine we have one zinc and then
two chlorines looking through this
and then we also have two hydrogens
going through this example so one thing
you're going to see really quickly is
the H and the chlorine are not balanced
we have two on the right hand side and
one on the left
so as a result what should we do to
balance it well a quick thing that you
could do is oh we should probably
multiply these by two to show that oh
this is going to be balanced on both
sides so we can see the zincs will be
balanced the hydrogens will be balanced
and the chlorines will be balanced so if
I add a 2 here
that is now going to be bounced so how
can we illustrate that well it's the
same thing as saying that oh I have one
zinc atom
reacting with two HCL
molecules
to create one zinc chloride
and one H2
so it's the same way as if moles being
in stoichiometry you'll have to do moles
this is one mole of zinc
two moles of HCL
one mole of zinc chloride and this is
from the coefficients and then one mole
of H2
so it's a way for us to illustrate all
those little different pieces to make it
a little bit easier
okay let's do another
so if we want to do one that might be a
little just do two little harder ones
so if I have sodium hydroxide
reacting
with magnesium nitrate
and that that is creating sodium nitrate
and magnesium
oxide
okay so we have this problem first thing
what we're going to do is we're going to
list out all the different starting
pieces
so we have sodium we have
magnesium now this is one of my biggest
tips notice how we have polyatomics in
this part of the problem what do I mean
by a polyatomic is that we have
hydroxide
which is a polyatomic
and then we also have nitrate which is a
polyatomic
write them down as one unit or one
species when balancing it's going to
make your balancing life a lot easier so
we're going to write down our
polyatomics so with these make sure that
you are able to recognize when you have
a polyatomic I'm going to show you why
here in a second so when we go through
the balancing let's count what we have
so we have one
sodium
we have one hydroxide
we have one magnesium
then we have two nitrates and the way
that we have two nitrates is by looking
at the
um
little two that's outside of nitrate and
that's how we know we have the two there
so
on the right hand side I have one sodium
one nitrate then I have one magnesium
and then two hydroxides okay how can we
go through and balance these so the
first way to bounce these is start is my
hint is start with the polyatomics
and what we're going to be doing is what
I refer to as the zigzag method
so how does that start so if we start
let's let's go with we'll go we'll go
with um
we'll start with the hydroxide on the
left hand side just because it's the one
closest to the to the beginning so if we
start right here what we're going to be
doing is balancing those hydroxide so we
had two on the right so we need to
multiply this by two
so we'll add a 2 out front
this also multiplies a 2 in front of the
sodiums
now when we have that and let me move
that 2 over because I'm realizing
getting cut off
is when we have that we're now going to
go to what it's connected to so we're
going to zigzag to what it's connected
to meaning we're going to check the
sodiums now
so sodium there's two on the left
there's only one on the right so how do
we balance that well we need to do the
same thing we need to add a two
on the right
now when we do that we're now going to
zigzag to our nitrate and try to balance
those
only one nitrate on the right hand side
there's two on the left looking at those
two so we already multiplied the one on
the right by two
notice how
they're now balanced
and as a result as you keep zigzagging
from its partner across back and forth
back and forth everything else ends up
balancing as well so it it bounces out
the whole problem for yourself this is
one of the biggest hints of polyatomics
I I couldn't recommend this anymore when
you're going through this
let's do one more which is a combustion
problem so combustion reactions can
sometimes be very tough to do
so what this looks like is that you're
always going to have some kind of
hydrocarbon
and it's going to be reacting with
oxygen
to create CO2 and water
so with these the big problem is that we
have multiple sources of oxygen on the
products notice how we have
oxygen here
and then we also have oxygen over here
so it leads to this weird imbalance
between them
when you have that my big suggestion is
try to make them even meaning when
you're adding them together notice how
with the oxygens I have two plus one
here make the overall total even It
generally leads to more like you're more
likely you're going to get the correct
answer by doing that
the other big thing with a lot of these
types of problems if it's not balancing
correctly meaning that you have to use a
fraction to balance it then you most
likely have to multiply the beginning
large hydrocarbon over here by a factor
of two or three to balance it
so let's try to do something simple so
the first thing that I would do is if I
were to try to balance out
these oxygens over here
we want to leave oxygen for dead last on
the left
because it's by itself use it as a
kicker leave elements
for last
and that way you can always use it as
your final step so the first thing I
would try to do is balance the hydrogens
so if I do that
with the hydrogens here notice how with
oxygen it's going to be making it an odd
number to balance out the number of
hydrogens on the left for the total
number of oxygens so we have two plus
three
this this already is setting you up for
failure
if that happens where you have an odd
number of oxygens start over
and multiply that first number by two
save yourself the pain and Agony now
multiply it by two
so what that means is if we had two
hydrogens at the beginning or two
carbons at the beginning we're
multiplying that by two
we're also taking the hydrogens
multiplying that two for a total of 12.
so we have a lot of them
now we can go through and try to balance
our problem
okay let's start with the carbons first
carbon is always a good one to start
with
so I have 4 on the left I need 4 on the
right
so when we do that we now have a total
of eight oxygens plus one so nine four
carbons carbons are balanced
next thing we're going to do is we're
going to balance the hydrogens
so being that we're working on this this
part of the problem over here
so we have a total of 12 on the left so
we need a 6 in front of that hydrogen to
make a total of six
and then we'll also multiply the oxygen
by six notice how I made this into an
even number so it's 6 Plus 8 total of
14.
total six total four
and then on the other side as well we
have
a total of
I just realized I did some math wrong
it's total 12. 12 and 4 over here now
with the Oxygen's last thing so that's
why I said save that element for last so
how being that we already have two
oxygens on the left hand side
how could we make it balanced for
ourselves well I need to multiply it by
a 7. to balance it so leave your
elements for last okay now if you were
to start this problem and let's say you
notice
if let's say you multiply that first
number a little prematurely and you can
see that everything is divisible by a
whole number so maybe it's divisible by
two or three you can divide all your
coefficients so you want to make sure
you have the smallest
whole number ratio
or coefficients so keep that in mind for
yourself
as you always want to have the smallest
whole number ratio so for example let's
say if I had um
two let's just make up a fake thing
let's say I had 2A 4B and that made two
a b
squared and that's what that made here
well if that created that well we can
divide all of these by 2 to simplify
these so if that's ever the case
make sure that you're always double
checking you have the simplest whole
number ratio I know there's a lot of
things that we're all learning at the
same time but keep that in the back your
mind
so this is just a tip for yourself
now the other big tip is you're just
writing coefficients it's the same idea
as how I was drawing these earlier
saying like as their individual
molecules we're not actually carrying
out math on these things so what I mean
by that is let's say if I take the two
HCL that I had here earlier and we'll go
back down
so if I have that 2 HCL
we're not going to carry out the math on
that and make it
h2cl2 like that is not correct so
coefficients just tell you that you have
a total number of molecules so what that
is is that we have
two hcls in this particular problem so
that's another tip of that we're just
adding up different mole values when
we're counting these okay so this is my
video on how to balance chemical
equations if you need I will be making
more on types of chemical reactions in
the near future and I hope that this
video helped and I hope to see you next
time please considering that subscribe
button so you get some future videos and
help in this has been Dr Dan and I'm
really excited that you're stopping by
for help all right see you all later bye
foreign